Finding Aid for [Published works of John Harvey Kellogg including books, pamphlets, and periodicals], 1874-1953
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
[Published works of John Harvey Kellogg including books, pamphlets, and periodicals] 1874-1953
Kellogg, John Harvey, 1852-1943.
0046 Aa 2
Printed books, pamphlets, and serials by John Harvey Kellogg, Battle Creek, Michigan physician, food scientist, and founder of the Battle Creek Sanitarium, on a variety of medical and health topics and explaining and promoting the remedies and treatments he espoused through his Battle Creek Sanatorium.
15 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Acquisition The Kellogg publications were acquired from a number of sources.
No further additions to the records expected.
The collection is open to research.
Battle Creek, Michigan physician, food scientist, founder of the Battle Creek Sanitarium
Printed books, pamphlets, and serials by John Harvey Kellogg, on a variety of medical and health topics and explaining and promoting the remedies and treatments he espoused through his Battle Creek Sanatorium
Subjects:
Battle Creek Sanitarium.; Food.; Hygiene.; Hygiene--Periodicals.; Kellogg, John Harvey, 1852-1943.; Medicine--Michigan--Battle Creek.; Public health--United States.
- Printed Books
  - The art of massage: A practical manual for the nurse, the student, and the practitioner (28th Thousand (Revised). Battle Creek: Modern Medicine Publishing Co. 1932 ) (Box 1)
  - Autointoxication; or, Intestinal toxemia...
    - (4th Thousand. Battle Creek 1919 ) (Box 1)
    - (Third Ed., 7th Thousand. Battle Creek 1922 ) (Box 1)
  - The Battle Creek Sanitarium diet list. (Battle Creek 1909 ) (Box 1)
  - Catalog of the private library of Dr. Kellogg (n.p. undated ) (Box 1)
  - Colon hygiene, comprising new and important facts concerning the physiology of the colon...
    - (2nd edition, revised and enlarged, Battle Creek 1916 [see also another issue, Box 6]) (Box 1)
    - (28th Thousand. Battle Creek 1917 ) (Box 1)
    - (32nd Thousand, Rev. Ed. Battle Creek 1929 ) (Box 1)
  - The crippled colon (Battle Creek, 1931.) (Box 1)
  - Dyspepsia, its causes, prevention and cure (Battle Creek 1879 ) (Box 1)
  - First book in physiology and hygiene
    - new and revised ed (New York, Harper & Bros. 1888 ) (Box 1)
    - (New York, American Book Co. undated ) (Box 1)
  - Second book in physiology and hygiene. (New York 1894 ) (Box 1)
  - First book in physiology and hygiene, for primary grades... (Translated and adapted for use in Chinese schools by John Fryer. Shanghai 1896 (Temperance physiology series, no. 4)) (Box 1)
  - Lessons in hygiene, for intermediate grades... (translated and adapted for use in Chinese schools, with additions on opium-smoking and Foot-binding, by John Fryer. Shanghai 1894 ) (Box 1)
  - Glimt af naturen. (Kristiana 1894 ) (Box 1)
  - Haandbag for hiemmet: omhandlende hygiejne, főde og diet... (Battle Creek 1882 ) (Box 1)
  - The health question box, or a thousand and one health questions answered.
    - (1st edition, Battle Creek 1920 ) (Box 1)
    - an encyclopedia of health ([3rd edition ?] Battle Creek 1925 ) (Box 1)
  - The home book of modern medicine, a family guide in health and disease ([2nd edition?] Battle Creek 1907 ), 2 volumes (Box 1)
  - The home hand-book of domestic hygiene and rational medicine. (Box 2)
    - ([2nd edition] Battle Creek 1880 ) (Box 2)
    - (40th Thousand, rev. and enl. Battle Creek 1897 ) (Box 2)
  - The household manual of hygiene. (Battle Creek 1877 [imperfect]) (Box 2)
  - Household manual of domestic hygiene, food and diet... (Rev. Ed. Battle Creek 1882 ) (Box 2)
  - The household monitor of health. (Battle Creek 1891 ) (Box 2)
  - How to have good health through biologic living. (Battle Creek 1932 ) (Box 2)
  - Hygiene of infancy, a book of practical instruction in the care of babies written especially for young mothers. (Battle Creek 1916 ) (Box 2)
  - Hygiène populaire et moniteur de la santé. (Bâle. 1897 ) (Box 2)
  - The hygienic family physician: A complete guide for the preservation of health and the treatment of the sick without medicine... (Battle Creek 1874 ) (Box 2)
  - Ideas. (Battle Creek 1916 ) (Box 2)
  - The iron ration. (typescript undated ) (Box 2)
  - The itinerary of a breakfast
    - ([1st edition?] Battle Creek 1918 ) (Box 2)
    - (6th edition, New York: Funk and Wagnalls, c1918) (Box 2)
    - (Rev. Ed. New York, c1926) (Box 2)
  - Ladies' guide in health and disease. Girlhood, maidenhood, wifehood, motherhood.
    - ([2nd edition?] Des Moines 1884 ) (Box 2)
      [imperfect]
    - (Battle Creek: Good Health Publishing Co. 1891 ) (Box 2)
    - (Battle Creek 1907 ) (Box 3)
  - Library of health (4 vols. Battle Creek 1904 )
    - Vol. 1. Boyhood and youth (Box 3)
    - Vol. 2. Manhood. (Box 3)
    - Vol. 3. Girlhood-Womanhood (Box 3)
    - Vol. 4. Wifehood -- Motherhood (Box 3)
  - Life, its mysteries and miracles, a manual of health principles. (Battle Creek, c1910) (Box 3)
  - Light therapeutics, a practical manual of phototherapy for the student and the practitioner... (Battle Creek 1910 ) (Box 3)
  - The living temple. (Translated into Chinese by Rev. M.C. Wilcox and Mr. Wong Cang-Hwo ... Shanghai 1912 ) (Box 3)
  - Man, the masterpiece, or, plain truths plainly told, about boyhood, youth, and manhood
    - (Battle Creek 1896 ) (Box 3)
      (imperfect)
    - (Battle Creek 1901 ) (Box 3)
    - (Battle Creek 1904 ) (Box 3)
  - The miracle of life. (Battle Creek 1904 ) (Box 3)
  - The natural diet of man. (Battle Creek 1923 ) (Box 4)
  - Neurasthenia; or, nervous exhaustion.
    - (1st edition, Battle Creek 1914 ) (Box 4)
    - (2nd Ed., enl. & rev. Battle Creek 1915 (Box 4)
      [See 2nd Ed., 3rd Ed., in Box 6]
  - The new method in diabetes
    - (1st edition, Battle Creek 1917 ) (Box 4)
    - (2nd edition, Battle Creek 1919 ) (Box 4)
    - (3rd rev. ed. Battle Creek 1924 ) (Box 4)
    - (4th ed. Battle Creek 1933 ) (Box 4)
  - The new dietetics, what to eat. and how, a guide to scientific feeding in health and disease
    - (1st edition, Battle Creek 1921 ) (Box 4)
    - (rev. ed. Battle Creek 1923 ) (Box 4)
    - (rev. ed. Battle Creek 1927 ) (Box 4)
  - The physical, moral and social effects of alcoholic poison, as a beverage and as a medicine. (Battle Creek 1876 )
    [Shelved separately: DA 2 K29.5 P578]
  - Plain facts about sexual life.
    - (1st ed., Battle Creek 1877 ) (Box 4)
    - (2nd ed., rev. Battle Creek 1879 ) (Box 4)
  - Plain facts for old and young.
    (first edition published 1877 under title "Plain facts about sexual life")
    - ([3rd ed.].Burlington, Iowa 1881 ) (Box 4)
    - ([4th ed.] Burlington, Iowa 1882 ) (Box 4)
    - ([5th ed.] Burlington, Iowa 1884 ) (Box 4)
  - Plain facts for old and young: Embracing the natural history and hygiene of organic life.
    - (New ed., rev. & enl. Burlington, Iowa 1889 ) (Box 4)
    - ([6th ed.] New rev. & enl., Burlington, Iowa, c1894) (Box 5)
  - Plain facts for old and young, or the science of human life from infancy to old age.
    - (20th Century ed., Third hundred thousand Battle Creek 1901 ) (Box 5)
    - (Battle Creek 1903 ) (Box 5)
  - Practical manual of health and temperance... (new ed., rev. & enl. 43rd thousand. Battle Creek 1887 ) (Box 5)
  - Rational hydrotherapy, a manual of the physiological and therapeutic effects of hydriatic therapy
    - (Advance sheets ed. Philadelphia 1901 ) (Box 5)
    - (1st ed., Philadelphia 1901 ) (Box 5)
    - (2nd ed. Philadelphia 1902 ) (Box 5)
    - (3rd ed. Philadelphia 1906 ) (Box 5)
    - (17th thousand. Battle Creek 1923 ) (Box 5)
  - Shall we slay to eat? (Box 6)
    - ([1st ed.] Battle Creek 1899 ) (Box 6)
    - ([3rd ed.] Battle Creek 1906 ) (Box 6)
  - The sinusoidal current as a curative agent; its history, technique and therapeutic applications. (Battle Creek, c1913) (Box 6)
  - Social purity: An address. 40th thousand. (Battle Creek 1888 ) (Box 6)
    (bound with: Ella E. Kellogg, A talk with girls: An address.)
  - An address on social purity. 100th thousand. (Battle Creek 1904 ) (Box 6)
  - The stomach: Its disorders and how to cure them. (Battle Creek 1896 ) (Box 6)
  - Sunbeams of health and temperance. An instructive account of the health habits of all nations... (Battle Creek 1888 ) (Box 6)
  - Ten lectures on nasal catarrh... (Battle Creek 1889 ) (Box 6)
  - Tobaccoism; or how tobacco kills. (Battle Creek 1922 ) (Box 6)
  - Tabacoísmo ó como mata el tabaco [Translated by Elias Chegwin] ([Barranquilla?, n.d.]) (Box 6)
  - The value of vibrotherapy as a therapeutic measure, its uses, effects, and techniques of application. (Battle Creek c1913 ) (Box 6)
  - Why the "blues," "nerves," neuralgias, and chronic fatigue or neurasthenia (3rd ed. Battle Creek 1921 ) (Box 6)
    [3rd ed. of Neurasthenia and nervous exhaustion.]
  - The everyday health series, by Kellogg, John Harvey and M.V. O'Shea ([? vols.] New York 1921 )
    - Book One: Building health habits. (other volumes missing) (Box 6)
  - The health series of physiology and hygiene, by Kellogg, John Harvey and M.V. O'Shea (New York 1915, 1921 ), 4 volumes
    - [no. 1] Health habits. (New York 1921 ) (Box 6)
    - [no. 2] Health and cleanliness. (New York 1921 ) (Box 6)
    - [no. 3] The body in health. (New York 1915 ) (Box 6)
    - [no. 4] Making the most of life. (New York 1915 ) (Box 6)
  - Essays in honor of Dr. I.P. Pavlov (n.p., n.d.) (Box 6)
  - (Contains three essays by John Harvey Kellogg)
    - "A visit to Pavlov's laboratory" (Box 6)
    - "The influence of irritating substances on the secretion of gastric juices (Chemical phase)", with W.N. Boldyreff (Box 6)
    - "A study of the mechanism of gastric contractions" (Box 6)
  - The business man's health library (Battle Creek 1916 ), 5 volumes (Box 6)
  - Vol. I. Colon hygiene Part I (Box 6)
  - Vol. II. Colon hygiene, Part II (Box 6)
  - Vol. III. Neurasthenia or nerveus exhaustion (2nd ed., Part I) (Box 6)
  - Vol. IV. Neurasthenia or nervous exhaustion (2nd ed. Part II) (Box 6)
  - Vol. V. Riley, W.H. Headaches and how to prevent them (Box 6)
- Pamphlets
  - "Abdominal respiration," (reprinted from Modern Medicine and Bacteriological Review, July, 1895. Battle Creek 1895 ) (Box 7)
  - "Abdominal section for dropsy," (reprinted from Modern Medicine and Bacteriological Review March 1893 ) (Box 7)
  - "Alcohol-A discredited drug", 2 copies
    - [copy 1] (n.p. undated ) (Box 7)
    - [copy 2] (n.p. c1920 ) (Box 7)
  - "Alcott's 'Potato Gospel'," (reprinted from American Potato Journal c1929 ) (Box 7)
  - "The American potato might have won the marathon," (reprinted from American Potato Journal, c1929) (Box 7)
  - "Antiseptic drainage in abdominal surgery," (reprinted from Bacteriological World and Modern Medicine, 1892 ) (Box 7)
  - "The apple a wonderful health promoter," ( 1925 ) (Box 7)
  - "Are we a dying race?," (reprinted from Good Health, 1897 ) (Box 7)
  - "The backward child," (clipped from Public Health, undated ) (Box 7)
  - "Bacteriology condemns meat," (reprinted from Good Health ( July 1922 ) (Box 7)
  - "Balanced bills of fare, arranged with reference to the normal daily ration, and the needs of special classes of invalids," (Battle Creek 1899 ) (Box 7)
  - "The Beef tea delusion," (Battle Creek, c1928) (Box 7)
  - "Benjamin Rush's great discovery." (n.p undated ) (Box 7)
  - "Biblical flesh eating." (Battle Creek undated ) (Box 7)
  - "Biologic antisepsis," (reprinted from The American Journal of Surgery, November 1926 ) (Box 7)
  - "The biologic life."
    - (Battle Creek, c 1920 ) (Box 7)
    - (Battle Creek 1930 ) (Box 7)
  - "A brief outline of hydrotherapy," (reprinted from Modern Medicine, June 1903 ) (Box 7)
  - "Cancer of the Stomach." (n.p., c1897) (Box 7)
  - "The case against meat eating," (reprinted from Irving Fisher and Haven Emerson, How to Live 20th ed., New York 1938 ) (Box 7)
  - "The cause of furunculosis," (reprinted from Modern Medicine, October 1895 ) (Box 7)
  - "A certain and successful method of shortening the round ligaments," (reprinted from Transactions of the Michigan State Medical Society, 1897 ) (Box 7)
  - "Chastity and health." (n.p., c1895) (Box 7)
  - "Chronic poisoning from the free use of flesh foods," (reprinted from Good Health, November 1897 ) (Box 7)
  - "Clean certified milk, versus pasteurized milk," (n.p., c1923) (Box 7)
  - "The climate of Mexico in relation to health," (reprinted from Good Health, January, 1895 ) (Box 7)
  - "Coffee a harmful drug." (Battle Creek undated ) (Box 7)
  - "The cold air cure: Frigitherapy." (n.p. undated ) (Box 7)
  - "Constipation-How to fight it." (Battle Creek 1913 ) (Box 7)
  - "Cow's milk, a cause of disease," (reprinted from Modern Medicine and Bacteriological Review September 1896 ) (Box 7)
  - "The cure of chronic invalids by regimen and training," (reprinted from Modern Medicine, November 1897-January 1898 ) (Box 7)
  - "The cure of incurables; Modern Medicine Library no. 4, August 1896." Battle Creek 1896 ) (Box 7)
  - "The daily ration: An experimental study of the amount and kind of food required daily by working man and women."
    - ([copy 1, n.p.,] 1895 ) (Box 7)
    - ([copy 2] 1899 ) (Box 7)
  - "Dangers in gasoline," (reprinted from Annual Report of the Michigan State Board of Health, 1887. Lansing 1887 ) (Box 7)
  - "A debate on vegetarianism between J. H. Kellogg, M.D., and Edwin Tenny Brewster, how to keep well; People's pocket series no. 123." (Girard, Kansas: Appeal to Reason undated ) (Box 7)
  - "The decay of American manhood." (Battle Creek 1917 ) (Box 7)
  - "Decomposing organic matter," (reprinted from Annual Report of the Michigan State Board of Health, 1882 reprint no. 128) (Box 7)
  - "Dependable methods of producing and maintaining an aciduric intestinal flora," (reprinted from Medical Journal and Record, September 18, 1929 ) (Box 7)
  - "Diabetes," (reprinted from Modern Medicine, September 1895 ) (Box 7)
  - "Diet as a means of combating acidosis," (reprinted from American Medicine, June 1916 ) (Box 7)
  - "Diet as a means of increasing vital resistance in tuberculosis, with special reference to the protein ration," (reprinted from Medical Record, February 13, 1909 ) (Box 7)
  - "Diet," (reprinted from I Illinois Medical Journal, 1927 ) (Box 7)
  - "Dietetic fads." (n.p. undated ) (Box 7)
  - "Dietetic importance of Florida fruits," (Senate document No. 7, 74th Congress, 1st Session. Washington, D.C. 1935 ) (Box 7)
    [from The Herald, Miami, Fla., July 1, 1934]
  - "The dietetic value of fruits," (reprinted from Modern Medicine, December 1897 ) (Box 7)
  - "The dietetic value of sugar," (reprinted from Good Health, November 1894 ) (Box 7)
  - Besredka, A. "Doctor Tissier and his work at the Pasteur Institute," translated by John Harvey Kellogg), (reprinted from Bulletin of the Battle Creek Sanitarium and Hospital Clinic, April 1929 ) (Box 7)
  - "Domestic sanitation," (reprinted from Annual Report of the Michigan State Board of Health, 1881 ) (Box 7)
  - "The effects of smoking on blood pressure," (Battle Creek undated ) (Box 7)
  - "The electric-light bath." (np. undated ) (Box 7)
  - "Electro-gymnastics as a means of increasing metabolic activity," (reprinted from Journal of Advanced Therapeutics, May 1915 ) (Box 7)
  - "Electrotherapeutics in chronic maladies," (reprinted from Modern Medicine, October-November 1904 ) (Box 7)
  - "Eugenics and euthenics," (reprinted from Good Health, August 1921 ) (Box 7)
  - "The eugenics registry." (n.p. undated ) (Box 7)
  - "The evil effects of alcohol," (reprinted from Good Health, March 1898 ) (Box 7)
  - "The evils of fashionable dress, and how to dress healthfully." (Battle Creek 1876 ) (Box 7)
  - "An exact method for determining the capacity of the stomach and the amount or residual contents," (reprinted from Modern Medicine, July 1896 ) (Box 7)
  - "An exhalation tube for lung development in the treatment of pulmonary consumption," (reprinted from Modern Medicine, November 1894 ) (Box 7)
  - "Experience proves the advantages of a meatless diet." (Battle Creek 1928 ) (Box 7)
  - "Experimental inquiries respecting the physiological effects of alcohol." (n.p., c1893) (Box 7)
  - "Experimental research relating to salivary secretion and digestion," (reprinted from Modern Medicine, February, May 1895 ) (Box 7)
  - "Experimental researches respecting the relation of dress to pelvic disease in women," (reprinted from Transactions of the Michigan State Medical Society 1888 ) (Box 7)
  - "The factor of safety in the human body."
    - (--, Battle Creek undated ) (Box 7)
    - (--, Battle Creek undated ) (Box 7)
  - "Filth germs in meat." (Battle Creek 1928 ) (Box 7)
  - "The first observed cases of Friedreich's ataxia in America," (reprinted from The Medical Record, March 7, 1914 ) (Box 7)
  - "Fletcherizing the oyster." (Battle Creek 1928 ) (Box 7)
  - "Florida sunshine and moonshine." (Westerville, Ohio: The American Issue Publishing Company 1929 )
  - "The flowers at evening prayer." (n.p. undated ) (Box 7)
  - "Food value of oranges," (reprinted from California Fruit Growers Exchange undated ) (Box 7)
  - "Good health and how to preserve it." (Battle Creek 1874 ) (Box 7)
  - "Graphic methods of recording diseased conditions of the lungs, and a new form of pneumograph."
    - [copy 1] (n.p. 1890 ) (Box 7)
    - [copy 2] (reprinted from. The Sanitarian, December 1890 ) (Box 7)
  - "The graphic study of electrical currents in relation to therapeutics, with special reference to the sinusoidal current," (reprinted from the Journal of the American Medical Association [1893 ?] Battle Creek 1902 ) (Box 7)
  - "The great destroyer." (n.p. undated ) (Box 7)
  - "Guelpa's discovery: The importance of fasting in the treatment of diabetes," (reprinted from New York Medical Journal, March 1916 ) (Box 7)
  - "Habits in relation to longevity," (Battle Creek 1928 ) (Box 7)
  - Boldyreff, W.N. "The harm of tobacco smoke" (4th ed., with foreword by John Harvey Kellogg. Battle Creek 1930 ) (Box 7)
  - "Healing magic." (n.p. 1923 ?) (Box 7)
  - "The health decalogue." (Battle Creek 1919 [two different copies]) (Box 7)
  - "Hot weather diet," (reprinted from Good Health, June 1897 ) (Box 7)
  - "How much does hypertension influence life duration or expectation?," (n.p. undated ) (Box 7)
  - "How not to be fat." (n.p. 1893 ?) (Box 7)
  - "How to get well fast." (Battle Creek 1882 ) (Box 7)
  - "How typhoid fever is propagated," (reprinted from American Lancet, 1889 ?) (Box 7)
  - "Hydriatic measures for regulating blood pressure," (reprinted from Rational hydrotherapy. Philadelphia 1902 ) (Box 7)
  - "The hydriatic method of the treatment of cardiac disease," (reprinted from Modern Medicine 1908 ) (Box 7)
  - "Hydriatic substitutes for alcohol," (reprinted from Bulletin of the American Medical Temperance Association, October 1901 ) (Box 7)
  - "The hydriatic treatment of chronic disorders." (n.p. 1901 ?) (Box 7)
  - "The hydriatic treatment of tuberculosis," (reprinted from The Medical News November 10, 17, 24, 1900 ) (Box 7)
  - "Hydrotherapy in cardio-Vascular disorders," (reprinted from Illinois Medical Journal March 1916 ) (Box 7)
  - "The ideal sanitarium." (n.p. 1890 ?) (Box 7)
  - "The immorality of smoking," (reprinted from Good Health, December 1922 ) (Box 7)
  - "The importance of intestinal asepsis and antisepsis in abdominal surgery," (reprinted from Modern Medicine and Bacteriological Review, 1895 ) (Box 7)
  - "Important new discoveries relating to digestion," (reprinted from Good Health ( 1892 ?) (Box 7)
  - "An improved instrument for draining the abdominal cavity after lavage in abdominal section," (reprinted from Journal of the American Medical Association, February 23, 1895 ) (Box 7)
  - "The incandescent electric light, or radiant heat bath." (n.p., c1895) (Box 7)
  - "Incompetency of the ileocecal valve-disorders arising from this condition and their treatment," (reprinted from The Medical Record, June 21, 1913 ) (Box 7)
  - "Incompetency of the ileocecal valve the most common cause of ileal stasis," (reprinted from The Lancet-Clinic, May 29, 1915 ) (Box 7)
  - "Incompetency of the ileocecal valve vs. Lane's kink as the cause of ileac stasis," (reprinted from The Medical Record, September 8, 1917 ) (Box 7)
  - "Increasing trench miseries." (Battle Creek undated ) (Box 7)
  - "The influence of alcohol upon urinary toxicity, and its relation to the medical use of alcohol," (reprinted from Bulletin of the American Medical Temperance Association, November 1895 ) (Box 7)
  - "The influence of different kinds of oil, introduced into the rectum, on gastric secretion," (reprinted from The Archives of Internal, November 1924 ) (Box 7)
  - "The influence of dress in producing the physical decadence of American women." (Battle Creek, c1891) (Box 7)
  - "The influence of irritating substances on the secretion of gastric juice (chemical phase)," (reprinted from the special issue of the Bulletin of the Battle Creek Sanitarium and Hospital Clinic, October 1929 ) (Box 7)
  - "Intensive methods of applying heat," (reprinted from Physical Therapeutics, October 1927 ) (Box 7)
  - "Intestinal stasis: Its significance and methods of combating it," (reprinted from The State Hospital Quarterly, August 1923 ) (Box 7)
  - "Intestinal stasis." (n.p. undated ) (Box 7)
  - "Is smoking harmful?," (reprinted from Good Health April 1927 ) (Box 7)
  - "It pays to be good," (n.p., c1916) (Box 7)
  - "[F.J.] Kellogg's obesity cures and other frauds," (reprinted from Journal of the American Medical Association undated ) (Box 7)
  - "Lawson Tait," (reprinted from Surgery, Gynaecology and Obstetrics May 1930 ) (Box 7)
  - "Lawson Tait and his contributions to abdominal surgery," (reprinted from Transactions of the American Association of Obstetricians Gynecologists and Abdominal Surgeons 1927 ) (Box 7)
  - "The liver." (Battle Creek 1882 ) (Box 7)
  - "The liver of dyspeptics." (n.p. undated ) (Box 7)
  - "Manual of explanations of a series of charts illustrating anatomy, physiology and hygiene." (Chicago undated ) (Box 7)
  - "Massage," (reprinted from Good Health c1890) (Box 7)
  - "The measure of a man." (Battle Creek undated ) (Box 7)
  - "Method for changing and reforming the intestinal flora," (reprinted from American Medicine June 1916 ) (Box 7)
  - "Methods of precision in the investigation of disorders of digestion." (Battle Creek 1896 ) (Box 7)
  - "Microbes and indigestion," (reprinted from Modern Medicine March 1895 ) (Box 7)
  - "Migraine, its causes and radical cure," (reprinted from Modern Medicine and Bacteriological Review October 1894 ) (Box 7)
  - "More nuts-less meat," (n.p., c1930) (Box 7)
  - "Milk as a food unsuited for the diet of adults," (reprinted from Modern Medicine and Bacteriological Review May 1895 ) (Box 7)
  - "Moulds in the stomach," (reprinted from The Medical News July 21, 1900 ) (Box 7)
  - "Movable kidney," (reprinted from Modern Medicine December 1893 )
  - "A national disgrace is our method for dealing with the insane," (reprinted from Good Health June 1926 ) (Box 7)
  - "The natural man as a vegetarian," (reprinted from Good Health undated ) (Box 7)
  - "Needed-a new human race." (Battle Creek 1914 ) (Box 7)
  - "A new and successful method of treatment of the opium habit and other forms of drug addiction," (reprinted from Modern Medicine June-July 1898 ) (Box 7)
  - "The new dietary." (Battle Creek 1899 ) (Box 7)
  - "A new dynamometer for use in anthropometry." (n.p. undated ) (Box 7)
  - "A new food for diabetics," (reprinted from Good Health August 1896 ) (Box 7)
  - "New form of posterior colporrhaphy," (reprinted from Boston Medical and Surgical Journal undated ) (Box 7)
  - "A new form of suture pin for use in perineorrhaphy," (reprinted from Journal of the American Medical Association November 19, 1887 ) (Box 7)